

#### KEY ACADEMIC SKILLS SUMMARY

Researcher - Lead- and co-author of 28 publications with 240+ citations on Google Scholar. **Collaborator** - Involved in multiple international academic and industrial collaborations. **Teacher/Mentor** - Extensive experience teaching courses and mentoring graduate students. **Community-Builder** - Member of multiple organizing/program committees.

#### LANGUAGE SKILLS

**English** - Native proficiency **French** - A2 proficiency (elementary)

#### **EDUCATION**

# Doctor of Philosophy (PhD), Computer Science

McGill University - Montréal, Canada

Title: A Symbolic Execution-Based Approach To Model Transformation Verification using **Structural Contracts** 

Supervisors: Hans Vangheluwe and Clark Verbrugge

# Master of Science, Computer Science

McGill University - Montréal, Canada

Title: Practical and Theoretical Issues of Evolving Behaviour Trees for a Turn-Based Game

Supervisor: Clark Verbrugge

## **Bachelor of Science, Computer Science**

University of Manitoba - Winnipeg, Canada

Honours Level, Co-op option with three work-terms:

#### **Assistant Software Engineer**

Fall 2009, Summer 2010

Electronic Arts Inc., Montréal, Canada

*Role:* Prototyping artificial intelligence in commercial video games.

## **Assistant Software Engineer**

Winter 2009

2019

2013

2011

Blackberry Limited (RIM), Waterloo, Canada

*Role:* Implementing cryptographic communication protocols.

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### **Post-Doctoral Researcher**

Université de Montréal - Montréal, Canada

Sept. 2021 to Present

Lab: GEODES Software Engineering Research Group Supervisors: Houari Sahraoui and Michalis Famelis

Research topic: Assisting non-machine learning experts in constructing machine learning solutions by exploring tailoring of computational workflows.

# **University of Antwerp** - Antwerp, Belgium

Sept. 2018 to July 2021

Labs: Antwerp Systems and Software Modelling, and Constrained Systems Lab

Supervisors: Hans Vangheluwe and Joachim Denil

*Research topics:* Verification and validation of cyber-physical systems, model-driven engineering, multi-paradigm modelling, co-simulation, and digital twins.

#### **Visiting Researcher**

#### Université de Montréal - Montréal, Canada

May 2018

Host: Eugene Syriani, GEODES Software Engineering Research Group

*Research topic:* Developing an interface between the AToMPM modelling tool and the ModelVerse modelling repository.

# fortiss GmbH - Munich, Germany

July to Aug. 2016

Host: Levi Lúcio

Research topic: Formalizing representations of model transformation languages.

# General Motors Technical Center - Warren, USA

Oct. to Dec. 2014

Host: Ramesh Sethu

*Research topics:* Applying model transformations for code/model modernization at an industrial scale, and industrial intellectual property concerns.

#### INDUSTRIAL COLLABORATIONS

# Framework for Systematic Design of Digital Twins (DTDesign)

2019 - 2021

*Project goal:* Develop a methodology and tools for industrial partners to efficiently and systematically build digital twins.

Main collaborators: Atlas Copco, Flanders Make

Topics addressed: Digital twin characteristics, integrating knowledge graphs and digital twins.

Publications: [Oakes2021, Oakes2021b, Oakes2023c]

Funding: Flanders Innovation and Entrepreneurship Agency (VLAIO)

## Automated & Simulation-based Functional Safety Eng. Methodology (aSET) 2018 - 2020

*Project goal:* Develop methodologies to reduce time and cost of the functional safety engineering process through automation.

Main collaborators: Dana Belgium NV, Siemens Industry Software (Leuven), Flanders Make *Topics addressed:* Verification of safety-critical cyber-physical systems (formal methods, fault injection using machine learning, simulation/visualization), DevOps for functional safety. *Publications:* [Bernaerts2019, Meyers2019, Moradi2020, Moradi2020a, Oakes2021a]

Funding: Flanders Innovation and Entrepreneurship Agency (VLAIO)

## Innovation in the Development of Electrical Systems For Aeronautics (INES) 2019 - 2020

*Project goal:* Provide a model-based systems engineering methodology for the development, validation, and verification of avionics systems to reduce time and cost.

Main collaborators: Boeing Research & Technology Europe (Madrid), Siemens Industry Software (Leuven), Flanders Make

Topics addressed: Co-simulation configuration, fault injection in co-simulation.

Publications: [Gomes2019, Moradi2019, Oakes2020]

Funding: Flanders Innovation and Entrepreneurship Agency (VLAIO)

# Network for the Engineering of Complex Software-Intensive Systems for Automotive Systems (NECSIS) 2013-2016

*Project goal:* Advance model-driven engineering tools and techniques for managing the complexity of automotive software development.

*Main collaborators:* General Motors of Canada Ltd., Queen's University, University of Antwerp *Topic addressed:* Verification of model transformations.

Publications: [Selim2014, Lucio2015, Selim2015 Oakes2015, Oakes2018a, Oakes2018b]

Funding: \$14M from Automotive Partnership Canada and Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC)

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Guest Lecturer Nov. 2022

Polytechnique Montréal - Montréal, Canada

LOG6953DE - Model-Driven Software Engineering

Professor: Mohammad Hamdaqa

Lecture topics: Model-driven engineering, usage and verification of model transformations.

# **Teaching Assistant**

University of Antwerp - Antwerp, Belgium

Professor: Hans Vangheluwe

Level: Graduate

2001WETMTR - Model-Driven Engineering

Fall 2020

Role:

- Developed and graded practical assignments utilizing model-driven engineering tools.
- Held virtual and in-person lab sessions to assist students with tool usage.

2001WETMSI - Modelling of Software-Intensive Systems

Fall 2019

Role: Developed and graded Petri Net assignment focusing on modelling and verification.

#### **Course Lecturer/Coordinator**

Winter 2015, 2017, and 2018

McGill University - Montréal, Canada

COMP 202 - Foundations of Programming - Six terms

Level: Undergraduate

Average enrollment per lecture: 189 students

Role:

- Developed and presented material for engaging course lectures covering Java programming topics, targeted towards students with no prior programming experience.
- Created multiple-choice, short answer, and long-answer questions and marking guides for course assignments and exams.
- Coordinated with other instructors and teaching assistants to ensure consistency in course material and meet teaching objectives.

# **Teaching Assistant**

2012 to 2014

McGill University - Montréal, Canada

COMP 202 - Foundations of Programming (x2)

COMP 250 - Introduction to Computer Science (x2)

COMP 251 - Data Structures and Algorithms (x3)

Level: Undergraduate

Role:

- Provided constructive criticism on assignments and offering helpful suggestions and resources via online class forums, tutoring appointments, and email.
- Marked exams and assignments in collaboration with other teaching assistants and provided feedback to lecturers.

# **Graduate Student Mentoring**

2019 to Present

*Role:* Strong co-author support, recommending publication venues, extending invitations to program committees.

Student	Degree	Institution	Co-Authored Publications
Matthias Bernaerts	Master's	U. Antwerp	[Meyers2019, Bernaerts2019]
Mehrdad Moradi	PhD	U. Antwerp	[Moradi2019, Moradi2020,
			Moradi2020a, Oakes2021a]
Bert Van Acker	PhD	U. Antwerp	[VanAcker2020]
Cláudio Gomes	PhD	U. Antwerp	[Gomes2019, Oakes2020]
Mouna Dhaouadi	PhD	U. Montréal	[Dhaouadi2022]

## **COMMUNITY BUILDING**

## **Lead Organizer**

## **Software Engineering at Montréal (SEMTL)**

Aug. 2022 - Present

2021

Summary: Regular mini-workshops of software engineering researchers in Montréal.

Website: https://semtl.github.io/

Attendance: ≈40 attendees per meeting, ≈30% are professors

Role:

- Leading organizational committee to define group vision and roadmap.

Model-Driven Engineering and Software Development (MODELSWARD)

- Coordinating with meeting hosts on content, venue, date, and maintaining website.
- Hosted Sept. 2022 meeting and presented current research.

## **Organizing Committee Member**

Annual Modeling and Simulation Conference (ANNSIM)	2022, 2023
Cyber-Physical Systems Track Co-Chair	
Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems (MODELS)	2022
Posters Co-Chair	
Session Chair	
Consortium for Software Engineering Research (CSER) Spring Meeting	2023

Journal	l Reviewer
---------	------------

SIMULATION	2023
Science of Computer Programming (SCP)	2023
Journal of Computer Languages (JCL)	<b>2022</b> , <b>2023</b>
Empirical Software Engineering (EMSE)	2022
<b>IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering (T-ASE)</b>	2021
Journal of Software and Systems Modeling (SoSyM)	2020 (x2), 2021
Program Committee Member	
Annual Modeling and Simulation Conference (ANNSIM)	2021, 2022, 2023
Workshop on Artificial Intelligence and Model-Driven Engineering	2022
International Workshop on Models and Evolution	2022
ACM Student Research Competition	2022
Spring Simulation Conference	2020
Summer Simulation Conference	2019, 2020

## **SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS**

– Journal of Software & Systems Modeling (SoSyM) Top 1% Reviewer	2020, 2021
– Best Student Paper Award at SIMULTECH	2019
for the paper HintCO – Hint-based configuration of co-simulations	
– NSERC Postgraduate Scholarship - Doctoral (PGS D),	2015 to 2016
Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada	
<ul> <li>Lorne Trottier Science Accelerator Fellowship, McGill University</li> </ul>	2015, 2016
– Harold H. Helm Fellowship, McGill University	2013, 2014
- Grad Excellence Award in Computer Science, McGill University	2012, 2014

# **PUBLICATIONS**

Links: 

tinks:

#### **Peer-Reviewed Journals**

- [Oakes 2018a] B. Oakes, J. Troya, L. Lúcio, and M. Wimmer, "Full contract verification for ATL using symbolic execution," *Software and System Modeling*, vol. 17, no. 3, pp. 815– 849, 2018
- [Oakes2023a] B. Oakes, M. Famelis, and H. Sahraoui, "Building domain-specific machine learning workflows: A conceptual framework for the state-of-the-practice," *ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology*, 2023. In review following a major revision. Available as a arXiv preprint arXiv:2203.08638
- [Oakes 2023b] B. Oakes, J. Troya, J. Galasso, and M. Wimmer, "Fault localization in dsltrans model transformations by combining symbolic execution and spectrum-based analysis," *Software and System Modeling*, 2023. Accepted

#### **Book Chapters**

- [Oakes 2023c] B. Oakes, A. Parsai, B. Meyers, I. David, S. Van Mierlo, S. Demeyer, J. Denil, P. De Meulenaere, and H. Vangheluwe, "A digital twin description framework and its mapping to Asset Administration Shell," *arXiv preprint arXiv:2209.12661*, 2023. To be published in Springer book of best papers from MODELSWARD 2021/2022
- [Karaduman2022] B. Karaduman, B. Oakes, R. Eslampanah, J. Denil, H. Vangheluwe, and M. Challenger, "An architecture and reference implementation for WSN-Based IoT systems," in *Emerging Trends in IoT and Integration with Data Science, Cloud Computing, and Big Data Analytics*, pp. 80–103, IGI Global, 2022
- [Oakes 2020] B. Oakes, C. Gomes, F. R. Holzinger, M. Benedikt, J. Denil, and H. Vangheluwe, "Hint-based configuration of co-simulations with algebraic loops," in 9th International Conference, SIMULTECH 2019 Prague, Czech Republic, July 29-31, 2019, Revised Selected Papers, vol. 1260, pp. 1–28, Springer, 2020

#### **Peer-reviewed Conferences**

- [Oakes 2023] B. Oakes, C. Gomes, J. Denil, J. Deantoni, J. Cambeiro, J. Fitzgerald, and P. G. Larsen, "Examining model qualities and their impact on digital twins," in 2023 Annual Modeling and Simulation Conference (ANNSIM), pp. 1–12, IEEE, 2023. In press
- [Dhaouadi2022] M. Dhaouadi, B. Oakes, and M. Famelis, "End-to-end rationale reconstruction," in 37th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering, pp. 1–5, 2022
- [Oakes 2021a] B. Oakes, M. Moradi, S. V. Mierlo, H. Vangheluwe, and J. Denil, "Machine learning-based fault injection for hazard analysis and risk assessment," in *International Conference on Computer Safety, Reliability, and Security*, pp. 178–192, Springer, 2021
- [Oakes 2021] B. Oakes, A. Parsai., S. V. Mierlo., S. Demeyer., J. Denil., P. D. Meulenaere., and H. Vangheluwe., "Improving digital twin experience reports," in *Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Model-Driven Engineering and Software Development Volume 1: MODELSWARD*,, pp. 179–190, INSTICC, SciTePress, 2021
- [Moradi2020a] M. Moradi, **B. Oakes**, and J. Denil, "Machine learning-assisted fault injection," *Position paper at SAFECOMP 2020*, 2020
- [VanMierlo2020] S. Van Mierlo, B. Oakes, B. Van Acker, R. Eslampanah, J. Denil, and H. Vangheluwe, "Exploring validity frames in practice," in *Proceedings of the First International Conference, ICSMM 2020, Bergen, Norway, June 25–26, 2020*, pp. 131–148, Springer, Cham, 2020
- [Gomes 2019] C. Gomes, B. Oakes, M. Moradi, A. T. Gámiz, J. C. Mendo, S. Dutré, J. Denil, and H. Vangheluwe, "HintCO Hint-based configuration of co-simulations," in Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Simulation and Modeling Methodologies, Technologies and Applications Volume 1: SIMULTECH,, pp. 57–68, INSTICC, SciTePress, 2019. Winner of the Best Student Paper Award
- [Moradi2019] M. Moradi, C. Gomes, B. Oakes, and J. Denil, "Optimizing fault injection in FMI co-simulation through sensitivity partitioning," in *Proceedings of the 2019 Summer Simulation Conference*, SummerSim '19, (San Diego, CA, USA), pp. 1–12, Society for Computer Simulation International, 2019

- [Lucio2015] L. Lúcio, B. Oakes, C. Gomes, G. Selim, J. Dingel, J. Cordy, and H. Vangheluwe, "SyVOLT: Full model transformation verification using contracts," in Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems (MODELS), pp. 24–27, 2015
- [Oakes 2015] B. Oakes, J. Troya, L. Lúcio, and M. Wimmer, "Fully verifying transformation contracts for declarative ATL," in *Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems (MODELS)*, pp. 256–265, 2015
- [Selim2014] G. Selim, L. Lúcio, J. Cordy, J. Dingel, and B. Oakes, "Specification and verification of graph-based model transformation properties," in *Proceedings of International Conference on Graph Transformation*, pp. 113–129, Springer, 2014

# **Peer-reviewed Workshops**

- [Oakes2021b] B. Oakes, B. Meyers, D. Janssens, and H. Vangheluwe, "Structuring and accessing knowledge for historical and streaming digital twins," in *First Workshop on Ontology-Driven Conceptual Modeling of Digital Twins*, pp. 1–13, 2021
- [Moradi2020] M. Moradi, B. Oakes, M. Saraoglu, A. Morozov, K. Janschek, and J. Denil, "Exploring fault parameter space using reinforcement learning-based fault injection," in 2020 50th Annual IEEE/IFIP International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks Workshops (DSN-W), pp. 102–109, 2020
- [VanAcker2020] B. Van Acker, B. Oakes, M. Moradi, P. Demeulenaere, and J. Denil, "Validity frame concept as effort-cutting technique within the verification and validation of complex cyber-physical systems," in *Proceedings of the 23rd ACM/IEEE International Conference on Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems: Companion Proceedings*, MODELS '20, (New York, NY, USA), Association for Computing Machinery, 2020
- [Bernaerts2019] M. Bernaerts, B. Oakes, K. Vanherpen, B. Aelvoet, H. Vangheluwe, and J. Denil, "Validating industrial requirements with a contract-based approach," in 2019 ACM/IEEE 22nd International Conference on Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems Companion (MODELS-C), pp. 18–27, Sept. 2019
- [Meyers 2019] B. Meyers, K. Gadeyne, B. Oakes, M. Bernaerts, H. Vangheluwe, and J. Denil, "A model-driven engineering framework to support the functional safety process," in 2019 ACM/IEEE 22nd International Conference on Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems Companion (MODELS-C), pp. 619–623, Sept. 2019
- [Oakes 2019] B. Oakes, R. Franceschini, S. Van Mierlo, and H. Vangheluwe, "The computational notebook paradigm for multi-paradigm modeling," in 2019 ACM/IEEE 22nd International Conference on Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems Companion (MODELS-C), pp. 449–454, Sept. 2019
- [Oakes 2018b] B. Oakes, C. Verbrugge, L. Lúcio, and H. Vangheluwe, "Debugging of model transformations and contracts in SyVOLT," in *Proceedings of the MDEbug Workshop at Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems (MODELS)*, pp. 532–537, 2018
- [Selim2015] G. Selim, J. Cordy, J. Dingel, L. Lúcio, and B. Oakes, "Finding and fixing bugs in model transformations with formal verification: An experience report," in *Proceedings of Analysis of Model Transformations Workshop at Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems*, pp. 26–35, 2015

#### **Technical Reports and Theses**

- [Oakes 2018] B. Oakes, A Symbolic Execution-Based Approach to Model Transformation Verification Using Structural Contracts. PhD thesis, McGill University, 2018
- [Lucio2014] L. Lúcio, B. Oakes, and H. Vangheluwe, "A technique for symbolically verifying properties of graph-based model transformations," Tech. Rep. SOCS-TR-2014.1, McGill University, 2014
- [Oakes2014] B. Oakes, "Optimizing Simulink models," Tech. Rep. CS-TR-2014.5, McGill University, 2014
- [Oakes2013] B. Oakes, Practical and Theoretical Issues of Evolving Behaviour Trees for a Turn-Based Game. PhD thesis, McGill University, Aug. 2013
- [Oakes2012a] B. Oakes, "Embedding causal block diagrams within behaviour trees,"
   Tech. Rep. COMP 522 Modelling and Simulation Course Project, McGill University, Apr. 2012

# **In Preparation**

- [VaraminyBahnemiry2023] Z. VaraminyBahnemiry, J. Galasso, B. Oakes, and
   H. Sahraoui, "Improving repair of semantic ATL errors using a social diversity metric,"
   Software and System Modeling, 2023. Expected submission in July 2023
- [Gomes 2023] C. Gomes, J. Fitzgerald, B. Oakes, K. Pierce, P. H. Mikkelsen, S. G. Arboleda, T. Böttjer, and M. Sandberg, *The Engineering of Digital Twins*, ch. Foundational Concepts for Digital Twins for Cyber-Physical Systems, pp. –. Springer, 2023. Expected submission in October 2023